They're not just getting rich... They're getting even.
Trading Places is a comedy film directed by John Landis.
A snobbish investor and a wily street con-artist find their positions
reversed as part of a bet by two callous millionaires.
Louis Winthorpe III, played by Dan Aykroyd.
Billy Ray Valentine, played by Eddie Murphy.
Randolph Duke, played by Ralph Bellamy.
Mortimer Duke, played by Don Ameche.
Coleman, played by Denholm Elliott.
Ophelia, played by Jamie Lee Curtis.
Trading Places is a 1983 American comedy film directed by John Landis
and written by Timothy Harris and Herschel Weingrod.
Starring Dan Aykroyd, Eddie Murphy, Ralph Bellamy, Don Ameche, Denholm Elliott, and Jamie Lee Curtis, the film tells the story of an upper-class commodities broker (Aykroyd) and a poor street hustler (Murphy) whose
lives intersect over the Christmas and New Year holidays when they are unwittingly made the subjects of an elaborate bet to test how each man will perform when their life circumstances are swapped.
Harris conceived the outline for Trading Places in the early 1980s after meeting two
wealthy brothers who were engaged in an ongoing rivalry with each other.
He and his writing partner Weingrod developed the idea as a
project to star Richard Pryor and Gene Wilder.
When they were unable to participate, Landis cast Aykroyd—with whom he had worked
previously—and a young but increasingly popular Murphy in his second feature-film role.
Landis also cast Curtis against the intent of the studio, Paramount Pictures; she was famous
mainly for her roles in horror films, which were looked down upon at the time.
Principal photography took place from December 1982 to March 1983,
entirely on location in Philadelphia and New York City.
Elmer Bernstein scored the film, using Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart's opera
buffa The Marriage of Figaro as an underlying theme.
Trading Places was considered a box-office success on its release, earning over $90.4 million to become the
fourth-highest-grossing film of 1983 in the United States and Canada, and $120.6 million worldwide.
It received generally positive reviews, with critics praising the central cast and the film's revival of the 1930s and 1940s screwball comedy
genre, though they criticized Trading Places for lacking the genre's moral message and instead promoting the accumulation of wealth.
It received multiple award nominations including an Academy Award for
Bernstein's score and won two BAFTA awards for Elliott and Curtis.
The film also launched or revitalized the careers of its main cast, who
each appeared in several other films throughout the 1980s.
In particular, Murphy became one of the highest-paid and
most sought after comedians in Hollywood.
In the years since its release, the film has been praised as one of the greatest comedy films and Christmas
films ever made, though it has also drawn criticism for its use of racial jokes and language.
In 1988, Bellamy and Ameche reprised their characters for
Murphy's comedy film Coming to America.
In 2010, the film was referenced in U.S.
Congressional testimony concerning the reform of the commodities trading market
to prevent the insider trading demonstrated in Trading Places.
The film explores themes of new year's eve, prostitute,
philadelphia, pennsylvania, butler, christmas party.
The tone is lighthearted.